Alan Guedes — C.V.

London – UK

□ a.guedes@ucl.ac.uk • • • alanlivio.github.io • in alanlivio • ■ alanlivio • ■ alanlivio

Shorbio

I am Computer Scientist (PhD & Postdoc), and my career can be seen threefold. In research, I have contributed to projects on Multimedia & Machine Learning (ML) and participated in technical committees (ACM SIGMM and SBC WebMedia). I am currently interested in non-Euclidean ML methods for the next generation of immersive and multimedia systems. Second, I have added value to the industry by contributing to applied projects and standards at industry forums (ITU-T SG16 and BR TV Forum). While in teaching, I acted as an undergrad lecturer and postgraduate assistant. Also, I got involved in public engagement and promoted student interests in social impact.

Experiences

Work

UCL, LASP Lab

Postdoc Researcher on ML project

2021-today

Highlights: ACM SIGMM committees and workshop organizer; co-supervised undergrad students.

- SpheryStream (Funded by EPSRC) to Improve 360-video streaming with profile-based methods

PUC-Rio, TeleMidia Lab

Postdoc Researcher on ML & Multimedia projects

2017-2020

Highlights: project PI; team leader; standards contributions; SBC WebMedia committees and workshop organizer (students for social impact); co-supervised under/postgrad students; postgraduate lecturer assistant.

- VideoMR (Funded by RNP and Microsoft) to detect inappropriate content in video scenes;
- AML Anti-Money Laundry (Funded by BTG Bank) to detect financial transcations risk and anomaly detection;
- GT-RAP (Funded by RNP) to develipe a blockchain-based system for academic certificates;

Dynavideo, TV Division

Software engineer

2012-2012

Highlights: multiple awarded social impact project.

- Brasil4D (Funded by World Bank): design a transmission of social impact TV content to low-income families. Its results were published at a public report

Education

PUC-Rio

PhD. in Informatics. Thesis on Multimodal-multiuser support in multimedia scene descriptions 2013–2017 Highlights: thesis used in SBTVD standard; industry committees.

- PUC-Rio Ginga reference implementation, funded by PUC-Rio Software Licenses to TV manufacturers;
- From SBTVD Conformance Test Suite for TV manufacturers

UFPB

MSc. in Informatics. Thesis on Multi-device support in TV app stores

2010-2012

Highlights: thesis used in the awarded World Bank funded Brasil4D project; undergraduate lecturer; project leader

- GingaAppStore (Funded by RNP) to design broadband system to deliver TV applications;
- Art TVDI (Funded by RNP) to design agile methods for TV applications development;
- Ginga CDN (Funded by RNP) to develop reusable TV middleware components.

UFPB

BSc. in Computer Science

2005-2009

- Algorithms course undergraduate tutor;
- Part-Time software developer at Dynavideo TV Division to prototype TV software in ST boards.

Research

Publications.....

Google Scholar shows >50 published papers, >100 citations, h-index 6. See below recent and some selected publications.

Elsevier Book Chapter		2022
ACM Multimedia Systems.		2022
, ,	2016,	
IEEE Symposium on Multimedia (ISM).		2020
SBC WebMedia 2020, 2020, 2020, 2021, .	2021,	
ACM Symposium on Document Engineering.		2019 2019
IEEE Multimedia Signal Processing.		2019
Research Committees.		
ACM SIG Multimedia Reviwer and chairing	2020-i	oday
 Multimedia conference: reviewer (2022), area chair (2022), reproducibility chair (2023) Multimedia Systems (ACM MM): MMVE review (2021, 2022, 2023) and demo chair (2022) Immersive Experiences(ACM IMX) conference: reviewer (2022) and area chair (2022) QoMex conference (ACM QoMEX): reviewer (2023) Web and Mulimedia Committee of Brazilian Computing Society (SBC) 		
	2017-1	odav
- WebMedia conference: Steering Committee (2019-today), reviewer (2013-today), chair of workshop (2018), chair of Demos Workshop (2019-2022), and chair of Social Impact Workshop (2019-2022)	Undei	grad
Springer Reviewer	2022-1	oday
 Journal of Multimedia Tools and Applications: reviewer (2022, 2023) Iberoamerican Conference on TV Applications and Usability: reviewer (2020, 2021, 2022) 		
Industry Committees		
Brazilian TV Forum (SBTVD) Academic member at Techincal Module contributing to TV middleware standards	2017-	2021
International Telecommunication Union (ITU)		
Academic member at SG-16/Q13 contributing to IPTV middleware standards	2017-	2021
Teaching		
Experiences.		
PUC-Rio		
Lecturer assistant on Multimedia and Machine Learning to postgrad students (30)		2019
Lecturer assistant on TV development (Ginga Brasil, Funded by RNP) to undergrad students (30).	2013
Japan International Cooperation Agency Lecturer (and course design) on TV development to South American countries professionals(30)		2012
RNP ESR Assistant on Linux Administration to IT professionals (30)		2011
UFPB	20)	2010
Lecturer (and course design) on Programming Introduction (C language) to undergrad students	•	2010
Lecturer Assistant on Analysis and design of Algorithms to undergrad students (30).		2008
Public Engagement		
Chair of SBC WebMedia workshop to students researching on Social Impact.	2018-	
Brasil4D social impact project to low-income families.	2013-	2014
Funding & Awards		
Aproved Funding.		
Approved as PI in VideoMR project (Funded by RNP and Microsoft).		2019

Awards ACM Travel Awards 2017-2022 - SIGMM Travel Award for MMSys (2022) - SIGWeb Travel Award for DocEng (2017, 2019) - SIGHI Gary Marsden Travel Award for IMX (2022) Brasil 4D 2013-2014 - SET Conference Award for Best TV interactivity solution - TV Award Honorable mention in Innovation and Creativity - FRIDA Award for innovative TV technological solutions IPTV Application Challenge User-friendliness for GingaStore 2012 **Skills** Academic: Execute research agenda. Scientific and standard writting. Teaching: Course design. Presentation skills. **Programing**: Python, TensorFlow, Bash, C++, Lua, Java, JavaScript, Latex, Dcoker. Social: Good and empathic communication. Positive, make-it-happen, team-work, lead-by-example attitudes. Languages: Portuguese (mother tongue), English (fluent), and Spanish (fluent). Training..... UCL Data Protection for Researchers; Fundamentals in Research Funding. 2022-2023 Nature Interpreting Scientific Results; Focus on Peer Review. 2022-2023 ITU-T A.1: Working Methods of ITU-T Study Groups 2023

References

- Laura Toni, I.toni@ucl.ac.uk. Postdoc supervisor at UCL.
- Simone DJ Barbosa, simone@inf.puc-rio.br. PhD supervisor at PUC-Rio.
- Marcelo Moreno, moreno@ice.ufjf.br. ITU SG-16/Q13 and SBTVD collaborator.
- $-\ Roberto\ Azevedo,\ roberto. azevedo @disneyre search.com.\ Tele Midia\ collaborator.$